<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Anno Domini 1616. A confession and protestation of the faith of certaine Christians in England holding it necessary to observe, &amp; keepe all Christes true substantiall ordinances for his church visible and politicall (that is, indued with power of outward spirituall government) under the gospel; though the same doe differ from the common order of the land. Published for the clearing of the said Christian from the slaunder of schisme, and noveltie, and also of separation, &amp; undutifullness to the magistrate, which their rash adversaries doe falsely cast upon them. Also, an humble petition to the K. Majestie for toleration therein.</title>
            <author>Jacob, Henry, 1563-1624.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1616</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 77 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 36 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04211</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14330</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120216</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855415</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855415</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20908</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04211)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20908)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 993:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Anno Domini 1616. A confession and protestation of the faith of certaine Christians in England holding it necessary to observe, &amp; keepe all Christes true substantiall ordinances for his church visible and politicall (that is, indued with power of outward spirituall government) under the gospel; though the same doe differ from the common order of the land. Published for the clearing of the said Christian from the slaunder of schisme, and noveltie, and also of separation, &amp; undutifullness to the magistrate, which their rash adversaries doe falsely cast upon them. Also, an humble petition to the K. Majestie for toleration therein.</title>
                  <author>Jacob, Henry, 1563-1624.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[72] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>G. Thorp,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Amsterdam :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1616]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Henry Jacob.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D E⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Brownists --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Congregationalism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:20908:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20908:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anno Domini</hi> 1616.</p>
            <p>A CONFESSION AND PROTESTATION OF THE <hi>FAITH OF CERTAINE CHRISTIANS</hi> in England, holding it neceſſary to obſerve, &amp; keepe all Chriſtes true ſubſtantiall Ordinances for his Church viſible and Politicall (that is, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued with power of outward ſpirituall Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) under the Goſpel; though the ſame doe differ from the common or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Land.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed for the clearing of the ſaid Chriſtians from the ſlaunder of Schiſme, and Noveltie, and alſo of Separation, &amp; undutifull<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to the Magiſtrate, which their raſh Adverſaries doe falſely caſt upon them.</p>
            <p>Alſo an humble Petition to the K. Majeſtie for Toleration therein.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Coloſſ. <hi>2.6.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>As yee have received Chriſt Jeſus the Lord, ſo walke in him.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Pſalm. <hi>116.9.10.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>I will walke before the Lord in the land of the living. I believed, therefore have I ſpoken: for I was ſore troubled.</p>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="epigraph">
            <pb facs="tcp:20908:2"/>
            <q>Vide, &amp; Fide. Fide, ſed Vide.</q>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:20908:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A CONFESSION AND PRO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation of the faith of certain Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s <hi>in England, holding it neceſſary to obſerve &amp;</hi> keepe all Chriſtes true ſubſtantial Ordinances, for his Church viſible and politicall (that is indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with power of outward ſpirituall Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) under the Goſpell; though the ſame doe differ from the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon orders of the Land.</head>
            <head type="sub">Publiſhed for the clearing of the ſayd <hi>Christians from the ſlaunder of Schiſme and Noveltie, and alſo of Separation, and vnduti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes to the Magistrate, which their raſh Adverſaries doe falſly caſt upon them.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ee, who do beleeve &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs it to be neceſſary both for the glory of Chriſt, &amp; for the aſſurance of our owne ſoules, to obſerve and keep Chriſts ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Ordinances for his viſible politicall Church (which are wanting publiquely among us, &amp; yet are both his clear com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, and alſo ſpecial meanes
<pb facs="tcp:20908:3"/>of ſalvation, and of Gods worſhip for us under the Goſpell) doe judge it moſt fit and reaſonable to publiſh and teſtifie to <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> all men in all plainenes, wherein particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly we doe conſent, and doe fully agree with the publique Churches in Engla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> And wherein we diſagree and differ fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> the doctrine publiquely received. And alſo finally to ſhew the inforcing reaſons that haue driven &amp; compelled us to take this way which wee doe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Touching the firſt of theſe, we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt before God and men that we unfay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedly and hartily agree to all the civil au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, Magiſtracie, and Government as it is received and ſtandeth by law eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed in the Land, holding it a moſt high offence againſt Almighty God, if any of us ſhould not with all readines &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience at all times ſubmit in all things (eyther actively, or paſſively) thereunto.</p>
            <p>Moreover wee doe likewiſe proteſt, that we refuſe not on occaſion to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate with the publique ordinary Congregations aſſembled for the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of religion in England: viz. where
<pb facs="tcp:20908:3"/>neyther our aſſent, nor ſilent preſence is given to any meere humane tradition. And we agree willingly to all the articles of faith and religion publiquely received and mainteyned among us: onely excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting thoſe points which hereafter folow mentioned, and are diſtinctly ſet down in the particular Articles of this our preſent Confeſſion and Proteſtation.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Then touching the ſecond thing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove mentioned, that is, our difference and diſagrement from the doctrine recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved publiquely in this land, thus we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare and teſtify in the preſence of God and men, that meerely being conſtrayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the cleare and unreſiſtable evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of Chriſts goſpell, (which ſayth<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 5.29.</note> wee ought rather to obey God then men) and not moved by any other con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceite, or vaine fancie, we differ and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agree from the ſayd publique doctrine, in Eight and Twentie ſeverall Articles,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>28.</hi> Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles.</note> all of them being of very great impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, yea moſt of them both ſubſtantial matters in Religion, and alſo ſpeciall meanes of ſalvation under the Goſpell.</p>
            <div type="list_of_articles">
               <pb facs="tcp:20908:4"/>
               <head>The Articles, wherein onely wee diſſent from the publique Eccleſiaſticall order, and doctrine in England.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Of Chriſts offices; namely his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheticall and Kingly offices.</item>
                  <item>2. Of the alſufficiencie of the Scripture.</item>
                  <item>3. Of Chriſts true viſible Church gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally.</item>
                  <item>4. Of Chriſtes true viſible politicall church in more ſpeciall manner.</item>
                  <item>5. Of Synods and Councells.</item>
                  <item>6. Of a Catholike or Univerſall Church politike, that is indued with power of outward ſpirituall go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment.</item>
                  <item>7. Of a Provinciall Church indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent.</item>
                  <item>8. How true viſible politike churches are in England.</item>
                  <item>9. Of L. Archbiſhops, and L. Biſhops Dioceſan and Provinciall.</item>
                  <item>10. Of the making of Miniſters.</item>
                  <item>11. Of our Communicating with the
<pb facs="tcp:20908:4"/>Pariſh Miniſters &amp; Pariſhes in England.</item>
                  <item>12. Touching Pluralitie Paſtors, and Non reſidents.</item>
                  <item>13. Touching Diſcipline and Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures.</item>
                  <item>14. Touching the number of Paſtors in each Church: and of the Paſtors ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary power and authority in managing the Churches ſpirituall affaires and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment.</item>
                  <item>15. Touching the prophane and ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous Mixtures of people in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation.</item>
                  <item>16. Of humane Traditions.</item>
                  <item>17. Of traditions Apoſtolike.</item>
                  <item>18. Of Prophecy.</item>
                  <item>19. Of reading of Homilies in the Church.</item>
                  <item>20. Of Chriſts deſcending into Hell.</item>
                  <item>21. Of Prayer.</item>
                  <item>22. Of Holy dayes ſo called.</item>
                  <item>23. Of Mariage and Burying, &amp; chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, as it is called.</item>
                  <item>24. Of Miniſters made alſo Magiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates by the State.</item>
                  <item>25. Of the gifts and Offerings of the
<pb facs="tcp:20908:5"/>faithfull.</item>
                  <item>26. Of Tithes and the Paſtors fitteſt and due, and neceſſarie maintenance.</item>
                  <item>27. Of the civill Magiſtrates duety &amp; charge ſupreamly to overſee and order his Churches ſpirituall matters, yet but civilly.</item>
                  <item>28 Touching the neceſſity that lyeth upon us (notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding) to obey Chriſt rather then man, (when they differ) in our uſing the true, and refuſing the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary eccleſiaſticall ordinances above ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="article">
               <head>Of Christs Offices; namely his Propheticall and Kingly Offices.</head>
               <p n="1">1. Wee beleeve Chriſts Prophetical, and Kingly Offices even in outward ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall (or religious) matters to be abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute and perfect. Where note that wee underſtand outward ſpirituall matters (or religious) to be outward matters uſed in the exerciſe of Religion, not for any naturall reaſon, nor for any civill uſe, but meere voluntarily; that is, ſuch things therein, as are of the authors meere vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary
<pb facs="tcp:20908:5"/>appointing. And though ſome perſons oppoſing againſt us, do account theſe any thing rather, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Spirituall mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; yet ſurely we hold them to be ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall and religious ſeeing they are volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie inſtitutions vſed onely in and for the exerciſe of religion, and are appropria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted thereunto. Alſo theſe outward mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters (we believe) are ſpirituall and religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous unlawfully and falſely, which are of mens inſtitution: they are lawfully, juſtly, and truely ſuch, which are of the inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and appointing of Ieſus Chriſt. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine where theſe men doe ſay, They neither intend, nor teach theſe things to be ſpirituall or religious. We anſwer, that maketh not the matter. They are ſuch in the very nature of the thinges, notwithſtanding. For mens wordes or intents make not the nature of theſe things, neither can they alter the ſame. Men indeed make theſe things in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of religion falſe, and unlawfull, in as much as they come meerely fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> men. But ſpirituall and religious they are of themſelves, viz. being ſimply voluntarie
<pb facs="tcp:20908:6"/>ordinances appropriated to the affaires of Religion, as they are. In the appointing therefore of theſe outward ſpirituall mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters (and religious) we believe (as is ſayd) thoſe offices of Chriſt to be moſt abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute, and perfect. Indeed ſo perfect in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very ſuch particular now, ſo alſufficient, and ſo neceſſary to be ſubmitted unto of all Chriſtians, as the ſayd offices of Chriſt were under the Law. We believe that Chriſt in theſe things (no leſſe then in matters inward concerning religion) is the foundation to the whole building even of his viſible and politicall Church now under the Goſpell, as well and as throughly as he was under the Law, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by God over all things (yea all theſe things) as the head to his ſayd Church which is the fulneſſe of him that filleth all in all things. And ſo wee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve Chriſt our Mediator (in the kinde, and nature of his offices) to be not chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged (much leſſe diminiſhed) but altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the ſame unto us now, as he was heretofore to his people the Iewes; as it is written.<note n="‡" place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.8. <hi>Act.</hi> 3.23. <hi>Luc.</hi> 19.14.27. <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.43.</note> Ieſus Chriſt the ſonne yeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terday,
<pb facs="tcp:20908:6"/>today, and forever. Yea we are perſwaded, if we ſhould believe other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, we ſhould rob Chriſt of his honour and give his glorie to others; which is a part of the higheſt ſacriledge that can be. And therefore where in this Article we are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tradicted by ſome, who ſay plaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that Chriſt in the Goſpell though he bee the Prophet, King and Prieſt to his Church, yet he is not the onely, or ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Teacher, Inſtitutor, King, and<note n="|" place="margin">The Appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of Gabriel Powell de Adi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aph. &amp;c.</note> Lawgiver, of his outward Church, nor of the viſible adminiſtration thereof, and namely not in the forerehearſed outward thinges: And likewiſe that Chriſtians now have libertie and free choyce for the ſaide outward thinges in the exerciſe of Religion, till mans Authority do deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine them; and that then ſuch outward things are neceſſary to be obſerved, but not otherwiſe. This we cannot conſent unto: but we renounce it, as highly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogating from the true, and due offices, and honour of Chriſt, as is above ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="article">
               <pb facs="tcp:20908:7"/>
               <head>Of the Allſufficiency of the Scripture.</head>
               <p n="2">2. Wee believe the holy Scriptures Allſufficiencie even in the ſayd outward matters ſpirituall, now likewiſe, as well as it was believed and profeſſed by all the faithfull under the Law. And for that reaſon we hold this ſenſe (which indeed was and is the onely true ſenſe) of the 2. commandement, viz. that (touching the generall matter thereof, or generally) it containeth onely in the exerciſe of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion free and voluntary Ordinances (that is) having no cauſe for their ſayd uſe nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in civility, nor in naturall Reaſon; but the meere will of the Author of them. Yea we believe, that ſuch ordinances both outward, and inward, private and publique doe wholly make the 2. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, both in the affirmitive and Negative part. They againſt us abroade in the land hold not this ſenſe of the 2. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement, but deny it. As likewiſe (with like diſhonour to Chriſt, which wee noted before, and with no leſſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace to his word)<note n="|" place="margin">Doct. Whig. in pref. againſt T. C. ſaith, <hi>it is a rotten princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</hi>
                  </note> they deny the Allſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiency
<pb facs="tcp:20908:7"/>of holy Scripture in the ſaid out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward pointes (as we believe) of faith &amp; Chriſtian Religion, and moſt materiall and weightie under the Goſpell. They call them circumſtances &amp; Accidents to Gods worſhip. But moſt unjuſtly. The Scripture indeed ſerveth not to ſpecifie circumſtances, or Accidents. Wee wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly agree to this. Neither did it ſo at any time. As namely not under the Law. But we deny this conſtantly (being there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in well aſſured) our matters in contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie are not circumſtances, nor Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents in Gods worſhip: And therefore alſo not indifferent. A circumſtance is,<note place="margin">A cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance.</note> which of it ſelfe and by the very nature of it hath ſometime, and to ſome per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons a helpfull, a profitable, and needfull uſe of Gods worſhip, yet is not any part of Gods worſhip, nor perpetually fit, nor meerely voluntarie, nor uſed onely ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. An accident is,<note place="margin">An Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent.</note> which being no way a part of Gods worſhip is ſometime in it ſometime not. A matter ſubſtantiall in the worſhip of God (and that which is a part of it) is of 3. ſortes. <hi>Either</hi> a thing
<pb facs="tcp:20908:8"/>not Civill, but properly pertaining to Gods worſhip, and yet a meere volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ordinance therein. <hi>Or</hi> a thing having abſolute neceſſitie in nature and naturall reaſon to be a part of Gods worſhip. <hi>Or</hi> otherwiſe which by the Scripture is plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly commanded or forbidden in Gods worſhip. Our matters in controverſie are all ſubſtantiall, of one of theſe 3. later ſorters, &amp; namely of the firſt. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore what ſoever of them is lawfull muſt be commended to us in the Scripture. Elſe they are all unlawfull, ſinnefull, and wicked. The ſeverall pointes we ſhall here preſently note in particular (at leaſt) namely theſe which follow.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="article">
               <head>Of Chriſtes true viſible Church generally.</head>
               <p n="3">3. Wee believe that (for more cleare underſtanding) Chriſts true Church is to be noted, and conſidered 4. wayes. <hi>First</hi> Chriſt hath a true Church<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.15. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.23.</note> Inviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, which is the Univerſal number of his elect. <hi>Secondly,</hi> He hath a Church
<pb facs="tcp:20908:8"/>Militant conſidered meerely as it is<note n="†" place="margin">Gal. <hi>1.13.</hi> Philip. <hi>3.6.</hi>
                  </note> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing, and ſuffering; that is, as the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall members doe profeſſe the true faith, and doe endure the oppoſition of ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies for the ſame. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> the church is taken for a Chriſtian family ſo well nurtured and ordered in Religion, that they are<note n="‡" place="margin">
                     <hi>1</hi> Cor. <hi>16.19.</hi> Bez. Anno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat. ibid.</note> like unto a litle Church. So a Church is figuratively, and metaphori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally taken. But none of all theſe is to our purpoſe. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> The Church is taken as the ſame<note n="|" place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 18.17. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.12.13. <hi>Act</hi> 1.26.</note> is politicall, or indued with power of outward ſpirituall policie, and adminiſtration of Gods holy ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, the meanes of ſalvation for mens ſoules. Now this Church under the Goſpell (and with this conſideration) is that which onely we doe here treat of, ſeeke, and deſire. And wee believe that the ſpeciall forme of this, that is, Chriſts viſible politicall Church under the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, and the particular kinde of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereof muſt be of divine Inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, they are matters ordinarily neceſſary to Saluation, &amp; they are matters of faith, matters of the 2. commandement, no
<pb facs="tcp:20908:9"/>leſſe then they were under the Law. Wee believe that theſe things are no cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, nor Accidents, nor Indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, nor at all changeable by the diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of men. But we believe that theſe are matters of Subſtance in Religion: and that by theſe things one viſible politicall Church differeth eſſentially or ſubſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally from another; to wit, in the nature, and kinde of the outward ſpirituall Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration thereof. As namely the Iewes viſible politicall Church under the Lawe, did ſubſtantially differ from the Chriſtian viſible politicall Churches un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Goſpell. And rather the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Dioceſan, and Provinciall and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Churches ſince Chriſt doe ſo differ from the churches which are but ordinary Congregations independent. Moreover Laying on of handes <hi>(Heb. 6.2.)</hi> ſet for the forme of making Miniſters under the Goſpell, is counted one of the ſix fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dations &amp; principles of faith there rehearſed. Which then requireth that alſo the whole outward ſpiritual admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration, and government of Chriſtes
<pb facs="tcp:20908:9"/>Church now muſt be ſuch; yea and the forme it ſelfe of the viſible politicall Church muſt then be a foundation of Religion, a principle of chriſtian faith, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily neceſſary, &amp; forever unchange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able by men. Wee doe not here think that all who of ſimplicitie doe erre in this foundation and principle of faith are of neceſſitie damned. We are not of ſo rigid, and ſevere an opinion. But we therefore hold it as a foundation and principle of faith, becauſe it is ordinarily neceſſarie to ſalvation, and forever unchangeable by men. Thus ſtandeth our faith in theſe pointes: ſo that they which hold con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarily, to wit, that theſe things are but circumſtances in Religion, &amp; accidents, ordayneable, and changeable by men, even from one forme to another, doe (as we believe) erre greatly from the trueth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="article">
               <head>Of Chriſts true viſible politicall Church in more ſpeciall manner.</head>
               <p n="4">4. Wee believe that the nature &amp; eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of Chriſts true viſible (that is, po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticall)
<pb facs="tcp:20908:10"/>Church under the Goſpell is a free congregation of Chriſtians for the ſervice of God, or a true ſpirituall bodie politike co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teyning no more ordinary Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations but one, and that indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent. Wherein chiefly 2. pointes are to be noted. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, that a true viſible po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticall Church under the Goſpell is but one ordinary Congregation: And this is to be ſeene plainely in theſe ſcriptures. <hi>Math. 18.17. &amp; 1 Cor. 5.4.12.13. &amp; 1 Cor. 11.18.20. &amp; 1 Cor. 14.23. Againe Act. 1.15. Act. 2.1.44. Act. 6.2.3.5.6. &amp; Act. 15.22.25. Alſo Act. 14.27. &amp; Act. 15.30. Moreover Act. 20.28. &amp; Act. 14.23. Gal. 1.2.21. &amp; 2 Cor. 8.1. &amp; Rom. 16.1. &amp;c.</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond point here to be noted is, That by Gods ordinance, this one ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary congregation of Chriſtians is a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall bodie politike; and ſo it is a free congregation independent. That is, It hath from God the right and power of ſpirituall Adminiſtration, and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in it ſelfe, and over it ſelfe by the common and free conſent of the people independently, and immediately under
<pb facs="tcp:20908:10"/>Chriſt, alwayes in the beſt order they can. Which theſe places doe prove. <hi>Mat. 18.17.19. &amp; 1 Cor. 5.12.13. &amp; 10.15. &amp; 7.23. &amp; 2 Cor. 2.8. &amp; 2 Theſ. 3.6.14. Act. 6.3.5.6. &amp; Act. 14.23. Act. 1.23.26. Act. 15.22.25. &amp; 1 Theſ. 5.21. &amp; 1 Ioh. 4.1. Rom. 16.17. Coll. 4.17.2. &amp; 3 Io. 10. Gal. 1.9. Gal. 5.1. Gal. 4.26.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="article">
               <head>Of Synods, and Councells.</head>
               <p n="5">5. Howbeit we acknowledge with all, that there may be, and that on occaſion there ought to be on earth a conſociatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Congregations or Churches, namely by way of Synods: but not a ſubordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or ſurely not a ſubjection of the congregations under any higher ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all authoritie abſolute, ſave onely Chriſts, and the holy Scriptures. They who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny this, mainteyning a Dioceſan and Provinciall (and neither wee nor they themſelves know what univerſall) viſible politicall Church both proper and repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentative, doe herein vary farr from the rule of the Goſpell.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="article">
               <pb facs="tcp:20908:11"/>
               <head>Of a Catholike, or Vniverſall Church poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tike, that is, indued with power of out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſpirituall Government.</head>
               <p n="6">6. It is demanded, doe wee deny an Univerſall viſible Church under the Goſpell? Wee anſwer, yea. Under the Goſpell Chriſt never inſtituted, nor had any one Univerſall viſible Church (that is Politicall) either proper, or repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tative; which ordinarily was to exerciſe ſpirituall outward government, over all perſons through the world profeſſing Chriſtianity. No ſuch Church (ſay wee) is found in all the new Teſtament. Therefore we now cannot acknowledge any ſuch.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="article">
               <head>Of a Provinciall Church independent.</head>
               <p n="7">7. It is marveyled, why we likewiſe deny, that under the Goſpell there is any true viſible politicall Church, Provinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all or Dioceſan; ſeing ſo we ſhall deny a true viſible politicall Church to be now in England, becauſe the Engliſh Church
<pb facs="tcp:20908:11"/>(as commonly it is holden) is properly a Dioceſan and Provinciall, or a Nationall viſible politicall Church. We anſwere, For our parts we acknowledge there are many true viſible, yea politicall Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es in England in ſome degree, &amp; in ſome reſpect: yet indeed we deny alſo a Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onall, a Provinciall, &amp; Dioceſan Church under the Goſpell, to be a true viſible politicall Church (whether wee meane the whole body, or the repreſentative part of ſuch Churches) though the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like practiſe among us, doth hould them for true politicall Churches. The rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why wee deny theſe alſo, is, Becauſe neither any ſuch is found any where ſet downe in Gods word of the new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, even like as there is no Univerſall Church viſible politicall there ſet downe. But onely a free Congregation, or ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Aſſembly is found in the new Teſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tament, as a litle before is ſhewed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="article">
               <head>How true viſible politike Churches are in England.</head>
               <p n="8">8. And touching the true viſible po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticall
<pb facs="tcp:20908:12"/>Churches which we acknowledge are in England, wee profeſſe and declare in this manner. Namely that each com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of true viſible Chriſtians aſſociated togither in one place (viz. a Pariſh) and profeſſing to ſerve God according to his will, in faith and order ſo farr as they knowe (ſuch as there are many in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land) the ſame is a true viſible politicall Church in ſome reſpect; that is, Though not in reſpect of the order of the ſtate (unleſs indirectly and by accident to it) after which they walke, and under which they ſtand in ſpirituall bondage: yet in Chriſt directly they are free, And ſo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly and eſſentially they are a true po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticall Church, as they are a company of true viſible Chriſtians united by their owne conſent to ſerve God, as a litle be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is noted. And thus they have free power of ſpirituall outward governme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t among themſelves, though they profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedly practiſe it not. But (eſteeming them by Gods word in their direct practiſe &amp; ſtate according to the publike procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, they are not a true politicall
<pb facs="tcp:20908:12"/>Church, nor free (directly) as they ſtand under and joyned to the L. Biſhops ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall dominion over them. Which bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage and want of ſpirituall freedome in themſelves our godly people generally ſee not: nor this, That (in right from Chriſt) they have this freedome to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empted from the unlawfull domination of the L. Biſhops aforeſayd. Neither think they ſo upon this matter as they ought, and as the perill of their ſoules re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth. Howbeit, yet all this (as<note n="‡" place="margin">
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 25 18. <hi>&amp;</hi> 17.15.</note> we judge) doth not ſimply diſanull that peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples being true viſible Chriſtians with us (ſo long as herein they erre but of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance) nor the aſſemblies from being true viſible politicall Churches in ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect and degree, as before is ſhewed. And therefore we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate alſo with them on occaſion, as before likewiſe is ſignified; viz. while in ſuch communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting wee countenance out no evill thing in them, which in many places, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times we need not doe. Whereof we ſhall preſently ſee further in <hi>Art. 11.</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="article">
               <pb facs="tcp:20908:13"/>
               <head>Of L. Archbiſhops, and L. Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops Dioceſan, and Provinciall.</head>
               <p n="9">9. Wee believe, that the ſpirituall of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, calling, and power, and adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of L. Archbiſhops, and L. Biſhops, Dioceſan and Provinciall, with their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferior Hierarchy, is contrary to the Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall order, &amp; ordinance of Chriſt eſtabliſhed in the new Teſtament, and not to be communicated with. The proofes whereof doe ſtand on the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of the 4. Article before, and on thoſe in the 10. Article next following after.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="article">
               <head>Of the making of Miniſters.</head>
               <p n="10">10. Wee believe, that the eſſence of Miniſters calling under the Goſpell, is the<note n="†" place="margin">1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.21. <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.17. 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4.1. <hi>Act.</hi> 14.23. <hi>Act.</hi> 6.3.5. <hi>Act.</hi> 1.23.26. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.24. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.3. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.23. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.22. <hi>Math.</hi> 18.17.19. <hi>&amp;</hi> 28.20.</note> Congregations conſent. We ſpeake of the ordinary Miniſterie, eſpecially of Paſtors. And it is proved thus. What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is eſſentiall in making of a Miniſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, at ſome time, and in ſome place, the ſame is eſſentiall ever. But the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations
<pb facs="tcp:20908:13"/>conſent is eſſentiall at ſometime, and in ſome place. This is without queſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; viz. in ſome places it was, when Chriſtians came firſt out of the Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian tyranny &amp; bondage of Rome; Alſo as it may happen it is now, and may be hereafter in like caſes. And alſo in the firſt converſion of the Indies, and other infidell Countries. Which even our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries (as they muſt needes) doe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe. Therefore the Congregations con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent is eſſentiall ever, and every where in the making of a Miniſter. Many there are by whome this concluſion is denyed; They hold the authority and conſent of a former Miniſter, to be eſſentiall to the making of a Miniſter: And ſo they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive &amp; hold the Miniſtery of the Church of Chriſt with us, to come (as touching the eſſence thereof) ſucceedingly from Antichriſt the Pope of Rome. Indeed there are but onely theſe 2. wayes (nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can be) to make Miniſters to us eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentially: And therefore in truth we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude a Miniſters calling is eſſentially al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes from the Congregations conſent.
<pb facs="tcp:20908:14"/>For any lawfull authority herein from the Pope, we acknowledge<note n="*" place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.15.16</note> none. And with all upon this ground, Wee (for our partes) cannot but believe it to be ſimply unlawfull, and ſinfull to fetch, receive, yea or to uſe a Miniſtery formerly recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from the Prelates: ſeing that hereby (and eſpecially by the expreſſe opinion that the Miniſtery of England deſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth from the Pope) beſide the maintey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of Romes pride, the foreſhewed order of God, and the<note n="†" place="margin">As before in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of this Artic.</note> Churches true right ſpirituall is moſt plainely violated and defaced, yea and (as we doubt) our perſons moſt deeply indangered of our lives by the<note n="‡" place="margin">
                     <hi>Eliz.</hi> 27.2.</note> Lawes verdicte in the rigor thereof. Becauſe the Soveraigne abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutenes and independency of our Land and Countrey in ſpirituall things is greatly impaired, abaſed, and diminiſhed thereby, to ſay no more of it. Finally upon this ground we alſo believe, that a Miniſter (ſo reputed) without any par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular flocke, is indeed<note n="|" place="margin">T.C. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>epl. <hi>.1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>1.</hi>
                  </note> no Miniſter.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="article">
               <pb facs="tcp:20908:14"/>
               <head>Of our communicating with the Pariſh Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters &amp; Pariſhes in England.</head>
               <p n="11">11. Firſt, we believe that to think we doe, or can receive a Miniſtery eſſential<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from a former<note n="‡" place="margin">Hebr. <hi>7.7.</hi>
                  </note> Miniſter or Prelate (in theſe dayes) is an errour, and the thing received is a nullitie in that reſpect.</p>
               <p>Secondly, this receipt in a Pariſh mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter with us maketh not a nullitie of the Miniſterie in him in every reſpect be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides; that is, it maketh not voyd all truenes of Miniſtery in him, as a belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Congregation (howſoever) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenteth to have him, and uſeth him, for their Miniſter. This conſent of the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly there (howſoever it be mingled other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe with errour) is not wholly voyd.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, concerning us, when on ſome weightie occaſion we joyne onely to that which is true in the ſayd Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and teſtify in the beſt manner we can that ſo we doe, alſo ordinarily leaving the pariſh congregation and Miniſterie for that their errour, and other ſuch like; and with all profeſſing, publiſhing, and prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſing
<pb facs="tcp:20908:15"/>freely and conſtantly the ſimple truth therein with our ſelves, this quitteth us (as we firmely believe) and ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly maketh us cleare from all evill, and appearance of evill in this matter.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, It being no evill nor any ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of evill juſtly in us, to joyne to the Pariſh Congregation and Miniſterie in ſuch reſpect, and ſo farr forth onely, as is aforeſayd; we ought (as we believe) ſometime on waightie occaſion ſo to joyne, and<note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Luk.</hi> 17.37. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.25. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.32.</note> we ſinne if we doe not.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="article">
               <head>Touching Plurality Paſtors, and Nonreſidents.</head>
               <p n="12">12. We believe Plurality-Paſtors, and Nonreſidents to be directly contrary to the order of God in the Goſpell; And therefore that now they are ſimply un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull; and likewiſe deputed, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted Paſtors by private authority, ſuch as our Curates are. And meere Lecturers are little better.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="article">
               <head>Touching Diſcipline and Cenſures.</head>
               <p n="13">13. Wee believe the true adminiſtring
<pb facs="tcp:20908:15"/>of the holy Cenſures to be by the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations conſent alſo. And therefore not to be lawfully done by an abſolute Dioceſan or Provinciall authority; that is, if it be without any neceſſary concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of conſent of that Congregation, which it chiefly concerneth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="article">
               <head>Touching the number of Paſtors in each Church; &amp; of the Paſtors ordinary power &amp; authoritie in mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging the Churches ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall affaires &amp; Government.</head>
               <p n="14">14. Wee believe each Church ought to have one Paſtor at leaſt: and that they may have moe then one, if the number of the Church, and their meanes be fitt for it, and ſuch plenty of choice may be had. Howbeit we judge that it is beſt, and moſt agreable to the laſt Apoſtolike practiſe, that even where many are, yet that one have (during life) a precedencie and prioritie in order and place (not in power) before the reſt. <hi>Revel. 2.1. &amp;c.</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20908:16"/>Touching their power and authority in Church government, we believe (whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be in each Church ſingle, or moe then one) they have all that they have, and nothing more, then what the Congregation doth commit unto them, and which they may (when need requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth) againe take away from them; Yea to their utter depoſing, and alſo rejection out of the Church it ſelfe, if ſuch neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie be. Howbeit otherwiſe while they are approved and ſtand in their place, we judge each proper Paſtor may and ought to be truſted by the Congregation with the managing of all points of their Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall affaires and government ſo farr, that he with his aſſiſtants (when he hath any) doe execute and adminiſter the ſame: yet ſo, that in matters of waight the whole Congregation doe firſt under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand thereof before any thing be finiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and the finall act be done in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the whole Congregation, and alſo that they (the ſayd Congregation) doe not manifeſtly diſſent there from.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="article">
               <pb facs="tcp:20908:16"/>
               <head>Touching the profane and ſcandalous mixtures of people in the Congregation.</head>
               <p n="15">15. Wee believe concerning mixtures of the open prophane with ſome manifeſt godly Chriſtians, in a viſible Church, though at once it doth not deſtroy eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially, nor make void the holines of that whole Aſſembly, yet truely it putteth that whole Aſſembly into a moſt dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and deſperate eſtate by ſuch their confuſion, and by ſuch extreame perill of further infection, eſpecially if they doe long tolerate the ſame among them. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that what ſoule ſoever in ſuch a Church ſtate deſireth to be in ſafety, ought with all diligence to leave that ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall ſocietie wherein he ſtandeth thus, and joyne to a better: Seing under the Goſpell there are more free ſocieties of Chriſtians, mo viſible Churches politike, then one in a Country, and ſome more ſincere then ſome: And all true Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded of God to keepe their owne ſoules ſound and cleare from con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagion,
<pb facs="tcp:20908:17"/>which is unpoſſible to be done ordinarily for any long time, where the viſible Churches conſtitution is ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mingled of bad and good, of open pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane and godly togither: for who can carry fire in his boſome, and his clothes not be burnt? And who can touch pitch, and not be defiled therewith? And who can eſcape, but (in a while) a litle Leaven, will leaven the whole lump; much more will it ſo come to paſſe, where there is a great quantitie of Leave<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for a litle Dowe, as now with us it is, wherefore in ſuch an inevitable preſent danger of our ſoules, doubtleſſe we ought to leave the worſe ſocietie, and to enjoy one that is &amp; may be ſincere. For by no meanes may we dare to be of<note n="|" place="margin">
                     <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.12.</note> no viſible Miniſteriall Church; if but 2. or 3. where we live, can be gotten to conſent and joyne to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geither in the name of Chriſt, and in the freedome of Gods word.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="article">
               <head>Of Traditions humane.</head>
               <p n="16">16. Wee believe all Eccleſiaſticall un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>written
<pb facs="tcp:20908:17"/>Traditions and Ordinances of men (being no circumſtances nor acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents) are (now under the Goſpell, even like as they were under the Law) un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truthes, and falſe poſitions, and errors in the worſhip of God. And that ſimply we ought not to be preſent in the prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſing of them, unleſſe we might conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niently reprove the ſame. Wee much miſlike therefore thoſe who hould (at leaſt) ſome ſuch to be now in theſe times both tolerable and profitable in Gods worſhip. Nay; we believe all Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces freely and voluntarily inſtituted in the exerciſe of religion to be indeed (and ſo to be rightly named) Gods worſhip ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther true or falſe, being (as they are) the proper matter, contents, and parts of the ſecond co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement in the decalogue; which alſo before is ſignified in the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d Article. This doctrine they who admit not, doe erre not a little even in the very nature and definition it ſelfe of the ſayd worſhip of God, and in the kindes and parts thereof; we meane of Gods inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted worſhip. Some particulars of theſe
<pb facs="tcp:20908:18"/>unwritten Traditions are, <hi>a Catholike Church politike, a Provinciall politike church independent:</hi> the proper <hi>Offices</hi> of their government, and the <hi>Forme and parts</hi> thereof. Beſide, theſe alſo are: <hi>The Cope,</hi> and <hi>Surplice, the Croſſe in Baptiſme, Knee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in the Communion;</hi> and the like. All which being in Gods worſhip, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent to it in ſpeciall wiſe, and meerely of mens voluntary inſtitution, we there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore renounce and doe utterly condemne as mens inventions ſpirituall, and will worſhip.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="article">
               <head>Of Traditions Apoſtolike.</head>
               <p n="17">17. We believe that every ordinance or inſtitution Apoſtolike (and that muſt unto us out of holy Seripture be proved to be ſo) is divine; that is to ſay, of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Authority, inſtituted of God, ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply unchangeable by men, and ſuch, that of right it ought to be uſed perpetually, &amp; univerſally among Chriſtians, unleſſe God himſelfe (by his owne worke) doe let it, and make it voide. They therefore
<pb facs="tcp:20908:18"/>doe erre much who hould, that it is rightfully in the Churches power to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and take away ſome thing (which hath been of ſpirituall and eccleſiaſticall uſe) appointed by the very Apoſtles, and that mentioned in the holy Scripture: And they alſo erre no leſſe, who ſay that ſomething truely Apoſtolike may be proved ſo to be by Traditions onely, without Scripture.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="article">
               <head>Of Propheſie, as the Apostle calleth it.</head>
               <p n="18">18. Wee believe that the ſober, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet, orderly, and well governed exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of expounding and applying the Scriptures in the Congregation, by the Apoſtle called Propheſying, &amp; allowed expreſſly by him to any underſtanding member of the Church (but<note n="‡" place="margin">
                     <hi>1</hi> Cor. <hi>14.34.</hi> &amp; v. <hi>1.39.</hi> and verſ. <hi>31.</hi>
                  </note> women) is lawfull now, convenient, profitable, yea ſometime very neceſſary alſo in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe reſpectes; The Churches order and allowance therein for each particular per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſo imployed, being firſt had. For it being lawfull privately by<note n="|" place="margin">1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.11. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.10.</note> private moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on:
<pb facs="tcp:20908:19"/>it muſt needs be more lawfull in pub-like, when it is ſeene needfull by the Church, and is performed under the Churches order, direction, and judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="article">
               <head>Of the reading of Homilies in the Church.</head>
               <p n="19">19. Wee believe that with us the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of Homilies in divine ſervice is not lawfull, but very unmeete for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation of the faithfull: namely where it is held for competent without the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment of a preaching Paſtor; where as a Paſtors diligent, diſcreet, and judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous preaching, and applying of Gods word, is the power of God unto ſalvatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ordinarily. Neither doth every of the allowed Homilies in every pointe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne godly doctrine.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="article">
               <head>Of Chriſts deſcending into Hell.</head>
               <p n="20">20. After the uſuall and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon ſenſe of this Engliſh word Hell, we believe that
<pb facs="tcp:20908:19"/>in the Creed this point is not rightly tranſlated, where it is ſayd, Chriſt (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing dead) deſcended into Hell. For the Scripture ſayth onely (and ſo likewiſe doe the originall words in the Creed ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nify<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>) that he was then under the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of death. And was in the place, where all other the godly deceaſed were; And that is all.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="article">
               <head>Of Prayer.</head>
               <p n="21">21. Wee believe concerning prayer: that though every<note n="†" place="margin">2 <hi>Chro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> 29. 30. <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 102. <hi>&amp;</hi> 92. <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.30.</note> forme of prayer pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed by men be not abſolutely nor ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply a ſinne, neither (as we judge) an Idol, nor an invention of man, nor a tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion of the 2. commandement; yet wee conſtantly avouch and profeſſe a preſcribed Leiturgy, or a booke of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon prayer by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandement inforced upon a whole Church rightly conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, to be uſed ſtill in the very ſame words whenſoever they aſſemble (in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of other praying) is not ſo profitable but rather hurtfull in many uſers of it,
<pb facs="tcp:20908:20"/>as making holy zeale, true piety, ſincere godlynes, and other giftes of Gods Spirit in many of them to languiſh, namely where it is made neceſſary, and in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall uſe, and when it is ſo long, as that the reading of it over, taketh up the whole time fit for one uſuall meeting to divine ſervice. And therefore we cannot think it any way co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>venient for our ſelves, nor meete to be impoſed; or to be ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived in any well conſtituted Churches: much leſſe, to be impoſed on a whole nation, leaſt of all, upon all Churches of the world. The new Teſtament teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth no ſuch matter, neither troubleth it ſelfe with indeavouring an uniformity in this point, but leaveth all Churches here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in to their godly liberty, wiſedome, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, and diligent conſideration of themſelves. Beſides ſuch preſcribed Leiturges were never uſed (in any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner) among Chriſtians, till late after Chriſt. The ſooneſt was after 300. yeares. And to be ſhort, by experience wee ſee too oft, moſt evidently they breed both an idle Paſtor, &amp; an ignorant, &amp; ſecure people.
<pb facs="tcp:20908:20"/>Therefore to follow herein the Chriſtian liberty, and diſcretion of the Churches, in the Apoſtles times, we hold it to be farr the beſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="article">
               <head>Of Holy dayes, ſo called.</head>
               <p n="22">22. Wee believe that under the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell there is not any holy day, (beſides the Lords day) nor any faſting day, or dayes conſtant, ordinary, and on certaine ſeaſons, or times of the yeare continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be obſerved. All ſuch obſerving of dayes we believe is againſt Gods word, not onely as being religious ordinances<note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 15.9.13</note> inſtituted by men (neverthought on by Chriſt nor his Apoſtles in all their time, who yet had the Holy Ghoſt leading them into<note n="‡" place="margin">
                     <hi>Joh</hi> 4.25. &amp; 14 26. &amp; 6.13.</note> all truth meete for Chriſtian people, and had more reaſon to inſtitute them then wee) but alſo as being directly forbidden in the 4. Commandement where God ſaying to man,<note n="|" place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.9.</note> 
                  <hi>Six dayes thou ſhalt labour, and doe all that thou hast to doe,</hi> he ſayth there alſo, <hi>but rest the Seaventh,</hi> for ſo did God himſelfe after the 6. dayes
<pb facs="tcp:20908:21"/>creation; whoſe example herein do thou follow. Now this Divine appointme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of a Seventh day onely to be kept holy, wee plainely ſee to be (for the equity, &amp; proportion, which is the ſubſtance ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of) avery Commandment of God unto us ſtill: and therefore of all men to be perpetually obſerved. Howbeit if God or the Apoſtles had ordeyned (beſide a 7. day) any other holy dayes particularly in the Goſpell, as God and his Prophets elſe where in the Law did ordeyne ſome beſides the Sabbath, then (notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding this Commandement) we would never refuſe ſuch holy dayes now, over and beſides the Lords day. But that in the Goſpell was not done; the Goſpell no where ſheweth any ſuch matter. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we believe it not, we cannot now but refuſe it. And yet againe, Dayes of thankſgiving, or faſting, which by men are appointed upon ſome ſpeciall occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and are to be uſed accordingly; that is, for the ſayd ſpeciall, and particular oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions ſake, and onely for a ſeaſon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient and fitting thereunto (but in no
<pb facs="tcp:20908:21"/>wiſe conſtantly, and continuingly, as is afore noted) ſuch dayes, I ſay, we ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove and allow, as having warrant from the Spirit of God both in the Law and in the Goſpell. But other then theſe, we neyther believe, nor allow any.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="article">
               <head>Of Mariage, &amp; Burying, &amp; Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as it is called.</head>
               <p n="23">23. Concerning making of mariage, and burying the dead, we believe that they are no actions of a Church Miniſter (becauſe they are no actions ſpirituall) but civill. Neither are Miniſters called to any ſuch buſines: Neither is there ſo much as one example of any ſuch practiſe in the whole book of God either under the Law, or under the Goſpell, without which warrant we believe it to be unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full whatſoever any Miniſter doth at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt at any time, or in any place, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally as a part of his miniſteriall office, and function. Wherefore we profeſſe and proteſt, that we earneſtly deſire that the Solemnization of holy Mariage might
<pb facs="tcp:20908:22"/>be performed by ſome Civill Magiſtrate aſſigned by higheſt authoritie thereunto. And when Miniſters doe in the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations ſolemnize Mariage, we teſtify that we believe that they doe nothing therein, neither can, but bleſſe this ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of God; as likewiſe they doe ſome time the initiation of a Magiſtrate; they doe not eſſentially conſtitute either of them. And for Churching of women, likewiſe we know no ground for it in Scripture, nor good reaſon at all, ſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to make it a neceſſary part of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters office in the publike divine ſervice.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="article">
               <head>Of Miniſters made alſo Magistrates by the State.</head>
               <p n="24">24. Wee believe that the joyning of Paſtorall miniſtery, and Magiſtracy to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in one perſon under the Goſpell is ſimply unlawfull, and contrary to the Text of the new Teſtament, which ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, <hi>It ſhall not be ſo among you, Ma. 20.25. Luke 22.26.</hi> And. <hi>Let him that teacheth waite on teaching, &amp; abide therein, Ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 12.17.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="article">
               <head>Of the gifts, and offerings of the faithfull.</head>
               <p n="25">25. Wee believe that there is a holy Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of the whole Church in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municating of their ſubſtance together by gifts, and offerings.</p>
               <p>Theſe gifts and offerings are given<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Numb.</hi> 28.2.18.8. <hi>Malach.</hi> 3.8.9.</note> to God; they are Gods properly and ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally belonging to God; he taketh them for his: alſo they are given to that parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Church of God; for which the gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers doe intend them.</p>
               <p>They are not meere almes, but (firſt) evident ſignes of true love to God: then, they are neceſſary meanes and duties re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired by God for the ſupportation, maintenance, and upholding of the ſayd Church, and of the ſincere worſhip of God therein.</p>
               <p>Theſe gifts and offering are meerely free and voluntary, yea every time the giver commeth to God with them.</p>
               <p>Theſe gifts and offerings are<note n="‡" place="margin">
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 3.9. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.24. 1 <hi>Chro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> 16.29.</note> reall ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices to God, and partes of his holy <hi rend="sup">‡</hi> worſhip and ſervice. Alſo, after they
<pb facs="tcp:20908:23"/>are given and received they are holy and conſecrated things, not goods for<note n="|" place="margin">
                     <hi>Levit.</hi> 27.26.29. <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>od.</hi> 13.13. <hi>Deut.</hi> 15.19.</note> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſecular uſe.</p>
               <p>Theſe gifts are ſome ordinary, &amp; ſome extraordinary.</p>
               <p>The time of offering theſe ordinary giftes is every Lords day. The moſt fitt, and comely ſeaſon and place for it is in the holy Aſſembly, then when the Churches uſe is to performe it.</p>
               <p>Nevertheleſſe they who are on juſt occaſion any ſuch day abſent, ought all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes to lay aſide for God and for his ſervice their portion, or rather Gods parte, and portion: and in due time to bring, or ſend it. Which is no leſſe ſanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifyed to the foreſayd holy uſe, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to God, then if the givers then had been preſent.</p>
               <p>Theſe gifts though they be free and voluntary in the givers touching the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular quantitie; yet that they doe thus give &amp; offer every Lords day ſomewhat (either more, or leſſe) is<note n="†" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.2. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.14.</note> a very com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment of God, and a fruit of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary obedience in man.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:20908:23"/>
               <p>The quantitie is thus farre pointed at in the Scripture, viz. According as the Lord hath proſpered every one. And ſome are in high grace with God, who give to God out of their penurie.</p>
               <p>The perſons, who are to give theſe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly giftes, are all and every member of the Church, except onely thoſe that receive maintenance therefrom at the hand of the Church. So that all the Churches members are givers, or receivers.</p>
               <p>They that receive are the Poore, and the Miniſters of the Church.</p>
               <p>Extraordinary offerings and giftes (which ſome out of ſpeciall Zeale to Gods glory doe offer beſides the ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry) are for the place, time, kinde, and quantitie ſuch as each giver ſeeth God may be the more honoured thereby.</p>
               <p>The ordinary offerings in the aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly are to be received by the Deacons, committed into the hands of the<note n="|" place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 11.30. <hi>Numb.</hi> 18.8.14.</note> Elders, and with their direction to be diſpoſed of by the Deacons.</p>
               <p>The Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandment of the Apoſtle to the Church of Corinth. <hi>1 Cor. 16.1.2.</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20908:24"/>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the gathering for the Saincts, as he ordeyned in the Churches of Gala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia alſo, viz. Every firſt day of the weeke let every one put aſide by himſelf, and lay up as God hath proſpered him. This ſhewing what the Apoſtle then required of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for an occaſionall reliefe of other brethren farr off from them, doth ſhew more that he requireth them thus to doe for their owne conſtant, ordinary, and neceſſary ſupportation, &amp; maintenance.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="article">
               <head>Of Tithes, &amp; the Paſtors fittest, and due, and neceſſary maintenance.</head>
               <p n="26">26. Wee believe that Tithes for the Paſtors maintenance under the Goſpell are not the juſt and due meanes thereof. Howbeit yet we doe not think theſe Tithes abſolutely unlawfull, if they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine voluntary: but when they are made neceſſary, we think them not ſo lawfull. The ſame doe we judge alſo of whatſoever other ſet maintenance for mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Goſpell eſtabliſhed by tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall Lawes. We graunt, for the Miniſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
<pb facs="tcp:20908:24"/>ſecurity ſuch eſtabliſhed maintena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce is beſt: but for preſerving due freedome in the Congregation, ſincerity in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and ſanctity in the whole flock, the Congregations voluntary &amp; conſciona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble contribution for their Paſtors ſuſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and maintenance is doubtleſs the ſafeſt, and moſt approved, nay it ſeemeth, the onely way: wherewith the Apoſtles cauſed their times to be content: neither did they take care for other order herein: which certainely they would, and ſhould have done, if other order had been bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Onely they are carefull (and that ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry religiouſly) commanding all Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of conſcience and duety to God to give (not ſparingly, but liberally, and not as almes, but as duety) for the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding, advancing, and countenancing of the holy worſhip, and ſervice of God, which is either much ſtrengthened, or weakened, much honoured, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſed amongſt men, according as the Paſtors maintenance is. To this end ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth that which is written:<note n="†" place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.7.9.11.14.</note> 
                  <hi>Who goeth a warfare at any time on his owne coſt? Thou
<pb facs="tcp:20908:25"/>ſhalt not muzzel the mouth of the Oxe that treadeth out the Corne; If wee have ſowne unto you ſpirituall things, is it a great thing, is wee reap your carnal things? God hath ordeyned that they which preach the Goſpell ſhould live of the Goſpel:</hi> or elſe a people (herein negligent)<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.8.9.</note> robbeth &amp; ſpoileth their God, will a man ſpoile his God? Wherefore<note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 3.9.</note> honour the Lord with your ſubſtance, and with the firſt fruites of all your increaſe; and<note n="|" place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.6.</note> let him that is taught in the word, make him, that taught him, partaker of all his goods. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo every one as hee ſoweth,<note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>v.</hi> 7.</note> ſo hee ſhall reape; And<note n="‡" place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 16.16.</note> none may appeare before the Lord emptie. By all which it is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, that Almighty God commandeth the people to mainteyn with their goods their miniſters. And (in the Goſpell) their maintenance to be free;yet honeſt, liberall, and plentifull: that<note n="*" place="margin">2 <hi>Chro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> 31.4.</note> they may be incouraged in the way of the Lord.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="article">
               <head>Of the civil Magiſtrates duety, and charge to overſee and order his Churches in ſpirituall matters.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:20908:25"/>
               <p n="27">27. Wee believe that we, and all true viſible Churches ought to be overſeene, and kept in good order, and peace, &amp; ought to be governed (under Chriſt) both ſupreamely, and alſo ſubordinately by the Civill Magiſtrate: yea in cauſes of religion when need is. By which right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full power of his, he ought to cheriſh &amp; preferre the godly, and religious; and to puniſh (as truth, and right ſhall require) the untractable, and unreaſonable. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit yet alwayes but Civilly. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we from our hart moſt humblie doe deſire that our gracious ſoveraigne King would (himſelfe ſo farr as he ſeeth good, and further by ſome fubſtituted<note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicat. for To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerat. p.</hi> 8.12.</note> civill Magiſtrate under him) in clemency take this ſpeciall overſight, and government of us, to whoſe ordering and protection wee moſt humbly commit our ſelves, acknowledging that becauſe we want the uſe of this divine ordinance, That therefore moſt greate, and infinite evills both to us, and even to the whole king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome doth enſue, and alſo becauſe of the ſpirituall Lords their governme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t over us.
<pb facs="tcp:20908:26"/>And notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding the ſpirituall Lords<note n="‡" place="margin">Ibid. pag. <hi>12.</hi>
                  </note> doe think it injury and wrong to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves not ſmall, if the King ſhould ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute civill Magiſtrates to this buſines, yet (as it is ſayd) that is Gods owne or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance; and to doe otherwiſe, namely to commit either ſpirituall or civill go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment (viz.Dioceſan, or provinciall) to Miniſters of the word, is evill; and (as we believe) a direct tranſgreſſion of the text of the Goſpell above rehearſed, in Artic. 4.10.24.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="article">
               <head>Touching the neceſſity, that lyeth upon us to obey Chriſt rather then man in our u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the true, and in refuſing the contrary eccleſiaſticall ordinances above ſpecified.</head>
               <p n="28">28. Wee believe that by the word of God all Chriſtians are bound (each one for his own part) to keepe &amp; obſerve ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually, and perpetually the Affirmative eccleſiaſticall Commandements, and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances in the Goſpell, as well as the
<pb facs="tcp:20908:26"/>Negative: That is, ſo farre as one perſon ſufficeth to performe the ſame, ſingly &amp; by himſelfe he ought ſo to doe; &amp; where ſome number are required (&amp; are ready) for the obſerving of any ſuch Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, there each chriſtian (which can be preſent with other) ſtandeth bound to give his conſent, &amp; to make one with them therein. Alwayes after the beſtor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der they can, and namely that maine or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der which is in the Goſpell: notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding whatſoever mans forbidding, or whatſoever affliction in the world ſhould followe upon it.</p>
               <p>But that, touching the uſe of Chriſts viſible politicall Church under the Goſpell, viz. A free independe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t c<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (preſcribed in <hi>Mat. 18.17.</hi>) is ſuch an Affirmative Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; Ordinance;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.17.</note> and it agreeth to that order afore named, as wee ſee in the Scriptures alleaged for the 2. point in the 4. Article.</p>
               <p>Therefore every Chriſtian is bound by Gods word to keepe and obſerve the ſame perpetually, ſo as is before declared.
<pb facs="tcp:20908:27"/>And namely this all are commanded (oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> requiring) viz. to tell ſuch a Church, and to heare ſuch a Church. Therefore all are commanded and ſtand bound by Gods word (ſo as before is declared) perpetually to have ſuch a Church, and to be members of it firſt.</p>
               <p>Further all ſimply are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.20.</note> to doe whatſoever Chriſt commanded the Apoſtles, and to<note n="†" place="margin">1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.21.</note> try all things, and to hold faſt that which is good. And to<note n="‡" place="margin">1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.1.</note> try the ſpirites whether they be of God. And,<note n="|" place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.17.</note> brethren marke them diligently which cauſe deſſentions and offences be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the doctrine which yee have lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and avoid them. Theſe duties we may very well doe according to that true order above noted if we enjoy ſuch a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Church (a free Congregation) as is before deſcribed: But wanting ſuch a Church, it is not poſſible for us to doe them which any good order, as is ſhewed. Therefore we all are ſimply commanded to enjoy and uſe an independent Church exerciſing ſpirituall government (a free Congregation) according as is before
<pb facs="tcp:20908:27"/>deſcribed; that we may obey God and keepe his Commandement given us in theſe places of Scripture. Which we ought to doe.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.1.</note> all are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded to ſtand faſt in the liberty wherewith Chriſt hath made us free, and not to be intangled in the yoake of bondage. Out of ſuch a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Church (a free Congregation) we cannot poſſibly obſerve and keepe this generall Commandement orderly &amp; or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily); but in it we may. Therefore here we are commanded alſo to be actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in ſuch a viſible Church, a free Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, and to uſe the ſame.</p>
               <p>Againe all are commanded<note n="†" place="margin">2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.15.</note> to ſtand faſt, and to keep the Apoſtles Traditions and Ordinances. But this forme of a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Church is one maine, and ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall Apoſtolike Ordinance. Therefore we are all co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded to obſerve &amp; keepe it, namely ſo as before is declared.</p>
               <p>Againe all are commanded to<note n="‡" place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 13 17 7 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.12.</note> obey their Paſtors, to follow their faith, to make much of ſuch, to<note n="|" place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 6.33.</note> ſeeke firſt the Kingdome of God; to<note n="“" place="margin">2 <hi>Fet.</hi> 1.10.</note> make our cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,
<pb facs="tcp:20908:28"/>and election ſure, (viz.) by walking in the true outward way; To obſerve the 2. Commandement in all the parts of it; a maine part whereof under the Goſpell is this forme of a viſible Church, and government.</p>
               <p>Laſtly this ordinance of Chriſt we ought to hold and keep moſt firmely, whoſoever gainſay it, becauſe in this eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate of a Church, the<note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 33.3. <hi>&amp;</hi> 134.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Eph.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.12.</note> promiſes of God are given and received; and no where elſe directly and ordinarily. And there is no promiſe to any indirect and accidentall conſtitution of a Church. Wherefore this direct and ordinary meanes of hope, and faith of grace and ſalvation we ought to preferre before our life. Remembring alſo that<note n="‡" place="margin">
                     <hi>Luk.</hi> 9.27.</note> willingly to refuſe and omitt the ſame, is no leſſe then damnation to any man.</p>
               <p>Thus then in all theſe ſo waighty points we are cleerely co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded to obey God ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> man. And God co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manding us to feare, &amp; to love, and to ſerve him, he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandeth us the neceſſary meanes, &amp; way of doing ſo, even that Church, in and by
<pb facs="tcp:20908:28"/>which ordinarily wee muſt doe ſo, that wee may be accepted. Which (under the Goſpell) is ſuch a free Congregatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as is<note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>In Artic.</hi> 4.</note> before made cleare. Where we ſee that this onely is now Chriſts true viſible Church, and no other forme of a viſible Church is. Wherefore we are all bound with all care to hearken to the expreſſe precept o the Holy Ghoſt concerning even this point, ſaying,<note n="‡" place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 30. 21.</note> 
                  <hi>This is the way walke yee in it.</hi> Which alſo the Harmony of Confeſſions teacheth, viz.<note n="|" place="margin">Harm. of Conf. French Artic. <hi>26.</hi> Dutch. Artic. <hi>28.</hi> Helvet. ch. <hi>11.</hi>
                  </note> That this we ought to doe notwithſtanding men of power and might ſhall ſay nay.</p>
               <p>Theſe (with the branches depending on them) are our differences, even all the matters wherein we diſſent from the uſuall and common opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion among us in this Land.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Now therefore (to come to the 3. and laſt point of this our Proteſtation) wee demaund and doe earneſtly crave of every in different chriſtian to anſwere us: what falſe things have wee here affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med? What on our part is evill? What
<pb facs="tcp:20908:29"/>is wicked in all this? If nothing, as wear firmely perſwaded in our ſoules that there is nothing; Then we pray, and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly intreate (in the bowells of mercy in Ieſus Chriſt) every one to pardon our Conſciences, in that thus doing wee ſtand to give actuall obedience to our Heavenly Lord and Saviour in his owne Commandements), and Ordinances: which alſo wee doe, that we may thereby (as by the onely true complete meanes) get<note n="†" place="margin">1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.18.19.</note> aſſurance of ſalvation to our ſoules, which otherwiſe we for our parts cannot finde. And otherwiſe (whiſe wee omitt thus to doe, and keepe not Chriſts ſayd Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandements) any with reproch may ſay unto us, <hi>ſhew us your faith by your workes; through workes is faith made perfect: But faith without workes is dead.</hi> And Chriſt ſayth, <hi>If yee love mee,</hi> then <hi>keep my Commandements.</hi> And, <hi>Not he, that ſaith, Lord, Lord, But he that doeth the will of the Father is juſtified.</hi> Whence verily wee ſee it plaine, and we know well, that not the talkers, nor diſputers of Chriſts will, but the doers ſhal be ſaved, (yea though men
<pb facs="tcp:20908:29"/>afflicte them for it,) and they that will have Chriſt to raigne over them; not<note n="‡" place="margin">
                     <hi>L</hi> 19.</note> they, that will not.</p>
               <p>Wherefore we humbly pray every up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right-harted ſervant of God to conſider, that it is not poſſible for us (knowing that which we know) to give this fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rehearſed due obedience unto Chriſt, but by walking in this way, which wee doe. Which alſo cannot be but firſt by eſchewing the evill, and then by doing the good. That is; firſt by renouncing to be ordinary and conſtant members of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Dioceſan, or Provinciall Church vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible politicall. (Becauſe the forme of theſe is wholly without Gods word in the Goſpell, yea contrary to it.) And then alſo of the Pariſhes (as naturall parts) depending on them, and on their Lord Biſhops; ſeeing theſe likewiſe doe both want Gods word, and add to it, &amp; ſtand in bondage in thoſe the above noted ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiall pointes, and meanes moſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant to ſalvation, which before have been declared. Wherefore thus farr forth onely wee leave our ſayd pariſhes alſo:
<pb facs="tcp:20908:30"/>but no further. That is, to be in them no ordinary and conſtant members: but members in them occaſionally we refuſe not to be, ſeing in them we finde (in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny places) very many true viſible chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, with whom we cannot (as we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve) deny publike communion abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely, and therefore on occaſion we of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer to communicate with our ſayd pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like congregations (or pariſhes) as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we have profeſſed; taking God to witnes that this we doe (not through a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny pride, or ſingularity, but) meerely out of neceſſitie of our duetie to obey Chriſt in his word, (as we believe that herein we doe) and to ſubmitt unto his word, and ordeyned meanes, &amp; to keepe his commandements, and to avoide abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in ſinne; which otherwiſe poſſibly we cannot ſee how wee can avoyd. Yea againe, and againe we teſtify that being forced meerely by conſcience, thus wee do, not knowing otherwiſe in our ſoules, how to anſwere it at the laſt day. Where we know no Magiſtrate, nor Prince ſhall be able to anſwere for us, if after the
<pb facs="tcp:20908:30"/>Light manifeſted we be found ſtanding in a wrong way contrary to Chriſtes ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Ordinance, as we believe this Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſan politicall Church is.</p>
               <p>Secondly hence it is, that we do joyne (each perſon onely himſelfe) humbly, and obediently to the evident way of the Goſpell, the moſt certayne true Church<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> eſtate ſet downe in the New Teſtament by Chriſt, and his Apoſtles, namely, to a free Congregation. Which truthes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (ſpecially in the 4th. Article) wee have ſufficiently ſhewed; binding our ſelves to proceede ſimply, and onely by this ſure rule, and therein to perſevere untill death: or elſe (when wee ſwerve) we acknowledge our ſelves juſtly worthy of the fearfull Cenſure of <hi>Excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> from that holy ſociety of Chriſtians, wherein to by Gods mercy we are now entered, where withall wee acknowledge our ſelves alſo worthily excluded from the ſpirituall Communion of Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple wholly, and every where, till wee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne by <hi>Repentance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wee ſay the feare of God conſtrayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb facs="tcp:20908:31"/>us hereunto: ſeing we cannot other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe finde in our hearts cleerely the ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of our ſoules; a matter above all things in this world, which wee, and all people ought to have greateſt regard of.</p>
               <closer>All glory be to God on high, and in earth peace, &amp; goodwill towards man. The grace of our Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt be with us all. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="supporting_quotations">
               <pb facs="tcp:20908:31"/>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Ier. 32.39.</bibl>
                  <p>One way and one heart.</p>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Cypr. de Vnit. Eccleſ.</bibl>
                  <p>Credere ſe in Chriſtum quomodo dicet, qui non facit, quod Chriſtus facere praecepit.</p>
                  <p>How can one ſay, he believeth in Chriſt, who doth not that which Chriſt commandeth.</p>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Caluin. Instit. 4.3.2.</bibl>
                  <p>Eccleſiae diſſipationem, velruinam potiùs, &amp; exitium molitur, quiſquis ordinem hunc, de quo diſputamus, &amp; HOC GENVS regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis vel abotêre ſtudet, vel quaſi minus ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarium éleuat.</p>
                  <p>Hee laboureth the ruine, and deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Church whoſoever he be, that endeavoreth to aboliſh this order, and THIS KIND of Government whereof wee treate, or maketh light of it as leſſe neceſſary.</p>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="petition">
               <pb facs="tcp:20908:32"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>AN</hi> HVMBLE PE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TITION TO THE KINGS MOST <hi>EXCELLENT MAIESTIE, BY THE</hi> Chriſtians notified in the fore-rehearſed Confeſſion and Proteſtation, (his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties ever faithfull Subjects) that of his good &amp; mercifull diſpoſition it would pleaſe him to give them Toleration and peace under him in their ſerving of God acording to their ſayd Confeſſion and Proteſtation.</head>
               <head type="sub">
                  <hi>GIve thy judgments to the King, ô God, &amp; thy righteouſnes to the Kings Sonne. Pſalm. 72.1.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Oſt gracious Soveraigne, your loyall and dutifull Subjects notified in the forerehearſed Confeſſion and Proteſtation of their faith, being well aſſured
<pb facs="tcp:20908:32"/>and firmely beleiving that this intent of theirs is honeſt, righteous, godly, chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, and of neceſſarie importance to their ſoules health, yet being alſo in moſt greivous dangers, &amp; heavy perplexities, ready every howre to be drawne into moſt miſerable diſtreſſes and calamities, for this their conſcience and obedience to Gods word, have their recourſe to your Sacred Majeſtie their onely hope in earth, and to you (as they ought to doe) they make their ſute in moſt humble manner on their bended knees. Beſeech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing you (as in effect they<note n="|" place="margin">Anno. <hi>1609.</hi> An Humble Suppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</note> formerly did, ſo now againe) to give unto them this favour, that peaceably and quietly they may worſhip God and ſerve him in your Highnes dominions where they dwell, after the tenour of their Confeſſion and Proteſtatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> here before expreſſed. Their enemies are rigorous and ſharpe in laying affliction on them (onely for this their conſcience toward God) both in their goods and libertie, if your Majeſtie will give way to them; wherein they pretend your Majeſties ſervice, and that they doe
<pb facs="tcp:20908:33"/>but your will. So that it is your good Grace onely that under God can help us, and give us ſecuritie from ſuch (we truſt) undeſerved evills. Many things induce us to preſume thus into your Majeſties preſence, and to be in all humble ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuters to your Majeſtie for this ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular grace from you. Yea, many reaſons, and ſtrong inforcements (as it were) doe move us hereunto, which we beſeech your Majeſtie graciouſly to heare. Firſt, ſeeing this is the eſſentiall order in the Goſpell of the viſible churches of Chriſt, which we follow: if he have ſet any or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of ſpirituall government at all in the Goſpell, which we verily believe he hath. And then wee beſeech your Majeſtie graciouſly to conſider, how can it be poſſible but that (for Chriſts glory and honour, and out of neceſſary obedience and duetie to him) we ought to walke in it, and humbly ſue to your Highnes for peace therei<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n, as here at this preſent in all ſubmiſſion and lowlineſſe we doe. <hi>Secondly,</hi> Becauſe this we perceive that the perill of our ſoules lyeth hereon.
<pb facs="tcp:20908:33"/>How can we there fore chooſe but with all diligence and dutifull affection ſeeke at your Majeſties gracious hands this bountie towards us, which ſurpaſſes all other benefites which in this world you can yeeld us. <hi>Thirdly.</hi> Foraſmuch as the contrary way unto us, the way of the L. Biſhops and their followers, is ſuch as giveth great, and moſt apparant advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to the papacie &amp; Church of Rome, and which leadeth many in this land di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly thither backe againe; partly for that there is in the New Teſtament much more ſhew and colour for a univerſall Church viſible indued with governme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, then for a Nationall or Provinciall Church independent, as this in England now is: partly alſo becauſe they openly profeſſe that all the miniſteries in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land are by ſucceſſion<note n="†" place="margin">Fr. Maſon of the Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cration of Bb. Anno <hi>1614.</hi>
                  </note> derived and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived eſſentially from the Pope, which indeed in their eſtate they cannot will, nor chooſe but ſo acknowledge. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore conſidering this, what hearte can ſuſtaine the due griefe, ſorrowe &amp; ſhame of this ſlander, of this diſhonour to God,
<pb facs="tcp:20908:34"/>of triumph and laughing to Antichriſt, of reproch to our land, wherein wee for our partes can bringe no other remedie, but our prayers to God for the generall good, and moſt humble requeſts to your Highnes for mercie herein toward our ſelves. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> for as much as if we ſhould deny this our faith, and violate our conſcience, and turne backe with them to the way of deriving the miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ſucceedingly from Rome, we are ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified with the very cogitation hereof: not onely in that this would argue in us breach of faith toward God, and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable levitie in our conſcience, but alſo we behold a fearfull ſentence in the<note n="|" place="margin">
                     <hi>Eliz.</hi> 27.2.</note> law of our land againſt all which ſo ſay and affirme. Avoyding therefore this per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexitie and danger, we have no way to ſerve God truely in, but this which here we profeſſe. And therefore cannot but ſeeke your gracious favour in permitting us with quietnes to enjoye the ſame. <hi>Fiftly,</hi> the integrity of our heartes, and loyaltie of our mindes towardes your Highnes Soveraigne power under Chriſt,
<pb facs="tcp:20908:34"/>doth animate us to looke toward your Clemencie in this our need; whom God hath ordayned to be a nourſing father, and defender to all the religious profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors of the Goſpell among your ſubjects. And therefore we crave of your Highnes herein to be good unto us. In what par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular? That you would afford us, and aſſigne to us ſome Civill Magiſtrate or Magiſtrates qualifyed with wiſdome, learning, and vertue to be (under your Highnes) our everſeers for our more peaceable, orderly, and dutifull cariage of our ſelves, both in our worſhipping God, ad in all other our affaires, at your pleaſure; To whom with all readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and ſubjection we are willing to be accomptable and anſwerable alwayes. We have none under <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> in our wants and diſtreſſes to have recourſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, but to your protection and goodnes at all times. Yea whether we obteyne mercy at your Majeſties hands, or no: Nevertheleſſe ſtill to you doe we apply; your grace we doe and will attend. And ſo together wee offer with all willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
<pb facs="tcp:20908:35"/>to receive the oath of your Suprema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, and that of Alleagiance likewiſe. <hi>Sixtly,</hi> Your Majeſtie heretofore diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered on occaſion your tender pitty and commiſeration towards the conſciences of your ſubjects, and thoſe being ſuch as more reſiſt your royall dignitie, then wee (through Gods grace) ever have, ſhall, or can doe by the tenour of our o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen profeſſion; which alſo your Majeſties wiſdome it ſelfe<note n="†" place="margin">Tortus Lyes. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> doth well diſcerne. Yet towards thoſe your ſubjectes (the Catholikes) in your Kingly affection &amp; Clemencie you have ſignified that<note n="‡" place="margin">Apol. p. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> you intend no perſecution againſt them for conſcience cauſe, and that<note n="|" place="margin">
                     <hi>p.</hi> 60.</note> you never laid any thing to the charge of any for cauſe of conſcience. This giveth us to have great hope and confidence, and to comfort our ſelves upon the ſame your royall word. And therefore alſo we ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture, to be ſuters to your <hi>Highnes</hi> in this our need, as now we are, for the due and ſweete effecte hereof towards us. Some perhaps will object, that we will not be content with our conſcience to
<pb facs="tcp:20908:35"/>our ſelves, but alſo we uſe meeting in private for the exetciſe of our religion: Weanſwer, our religion hath no manner of evill in it any manner of wayes, as by our fore rehearſed Confeſſion is made manifeſt before, <hi>thanks be to God.</hi> And for meeting in private, it is not that we deſire or delight in, the Lord knoweth. The publike places with peace and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection under your <hi>Highnes,</hi> would be in this world the greateſt bleſſing and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite, which our heart deſireth, or which could come unto us. But we dare not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect, neither doe we ask ſo great favour at your Majeſties handes; onely that in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate peaceably we might ſerve God with cleare and quiet conſciences according to the effect of our fore remembred Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, we in all lowlineſſe craue but your Toleration. For meetings of a Congregation to the joint and common exerciſe of Gods worſhip are neceſſary partes of religion, and duties in conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, as being Chriſtes very ordinance and commandement. Your Majeſties wiſdome underſtandeth perfectly that
<pb facs="tcp:20908:36"/>without ſuch meetings, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon prayers, and other actes of religion in a Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, God neither is nor can be ſerved, as he ought to be. Wherefore this duty we cannot in any ſafety of conſcience relinquiſh, or neglect, neither can our meeting thus (onely in a competent Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation) any way in the leaſt meaſure be prejudiciall or ſuſpicious to your <hi>Highnes</hi> peace or dignitie. But by Gods grace you (yeelding us this favour) ſhall every way ſucceede to the advancing of Gods true glory, and your Majeſties flouriſhing government here, and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after to your more ſure attaying of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall honour, and ſoules health. &amp;c. Theſe cauſes therefore (ô Gracious and Magnificent King) conſtraine us, and binde us to implore this your favour and ſuccor at this time, in this behalfe. And ſo being not ignorant of your gentle and gracious clemencie many times ſhewed to ſundry perſons on ſundry occaſions of no ſuch importance as this is to our poore ſoules, and (as we judge) to the cleerer demonſtration of your eternall
<pb facs="tcp:20908:36"/>happineſſe to come; we lay downe our cauſe at your <hi>Highnes</hi> feete, and thus commend our moſt humble ſuite to your gracious and mercifull conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration. Beſeeching the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to bleſſe and to honour your excellent Majeſtie, &amp; your roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all poſteritie, with all the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>name<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of Grace in this life, &amp; of everlaſting ſalvatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hereafter through <hi>Ieſus Chriſt Amen.</hi> ⸪</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
